[MUSIC PLAYING]
Hello, and welcome to the Data Journalism Podcast.
My name is Simon Rogers.
I am a Data Journalist, speaker, and teacher, and data
editor at Google.
And my name is Alberto Cairo.
I am a professor of Visualization
at the University of Miami, an Infographics designer,
and journalist, and also a book author.
We love using data to tell stories.
And the music you can hear is the sound of data,
made with two-tone, an app that turns numbers into tunes.
There's also the sound of football, American football,
that is, with a changing football school since 1920,
care of one of our guests today.
And this is the Data Journalism Podcast
that dissects the latest trends in data journalism
around the world.
In each episode, we will explore the latest in data journalism,
and we will chat with some of the world's top data journalists.
You'll get to find out how they do what they do.
So subscribe at datajournalismpodcast.com
to see how data is changing the world of journalism forever.
Hi, Simon.
Hey, Alberto.
How are you doing?
So good.
I'm really thrilled to have the chat that we had this week.
It was a lot of fun.
It was a very interesting one, right?
Can you tell us a little bit about our guests?
Yeah, so we have two doyen of local data journalism.
We've got Ben Welsh from the LA Times, who
has been just one of the first people out there
to really see the power of using data to tell stories.
The Los Angeles Times have one of the first great data
journalism sections, and he has forgotten more than we will ever
learn about how data can just improve local reporting.
And we also are lucky enough to have Mary Jo Webster, who
is a great local reporter who's just taught herself
how to work in this area and really created
some interesting work.
It was a very interesting conversation with both of them,
and we got into sort of how they got started,
how they discovered the tools that they use nowadays,
beginning with Excel.
They tell a couple of funny stories
about how they discovered Excel and then later more
sophisticated data analysis tools.
I think that it was a very enlightening conversation,
and listeners will enjoy it a lot.
We should do an episode one day about Excel
and the power of this tool in getting people
into data journalism.
Love it or hate it.
It's just become this kind of like entry-level drug
for people who are getting into data and reporting.
I mean, it's super useful.
You can do amazing things in Excel, right?
I mean, both Ben and Mary Jo, they
mentioned AR, the programming language, and Python,
and many other tools.
But both of them say, you know, if you
can get away with doing this very simple thing with Excel,
why don't do it with Excel?
Or if you are getting started in this field,
it's better to begin with the tools that you already know
and many people already know that it's Excel, right?
Yeah, and one of the things we wanted to do with this episode
was really getting some of the nitty-gritty.
So we have a rapid-fire series of questions at the end,
really about the kind of people's top tools,
some of their foibles, some of the stories they care about.
It's a lot of fun.
And I would really advise sticking around to that,
because you'll learn a lot about how each of them works.
It was an excellent episode, I think.
So let's get into it.
Let's get into it.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Hi, I'm Mary Jo Webster.
I'm the data editor at the Star Tribune in Minneapolis.
And hello, I'm Ben Welsh.
I live in Los Angeles, where I work on a project
at Stanford University called Big Local News
and at the Los Angeles Times.
Thank you so much for joining us, Mary Jo and Ben.
We're really happy to have you both here today to talk really
about local data journalism and how it's
growing around the country, and I think around the world
as well.
But I would love you to talk a little bit first about how
you got into this world.
Now, Ben, when I was at The Guardian back in the day,
when we were setting up the data blog,
we were definitely looking at the work
that you guys were doing.
And I feel like you were actually really
one of the innovators in this field.
So talk to me a little bit about how
you got into data journalism and the kind of work that you do.
Well, it definitely wasn't the plan.
It wasn't anything that happened on purpose,
but I'm really glad it did.
I was a pretty listless undergraduate in Chicago,
Illinois at DePaul University and kind of unclear
of where I was going with my life and career,
like perhaps many undergraduates that Alberto
encounters from time to time, and maybe himself as well.
And I won't bore you with the whole long story,
but through sort of an unusual series of events,
I became the assistant to two local television journalists
in Chicago, who were both excellent practitioners.
And I became what was known at that time
as the foot man, which was a very glorified term
for the intern or the helper around the office.
And so as they prepare a weekly newspaper column
and television piece, I would do research and scheduling
and a little bit of television editing too.
And in that, I kind of caught the journalism bug.
And one of the early stories we worked on
was about corruption in a Chicago suburb.
Locals could probably guess which ones.
And we did my first public records request
for legal fees from a sort of local heavy
who was milking the city out of money.
And it came as a really, really long printout.
Remember when printouts used to have the perforated tears
along each side and a single print over 20, 30 pages
will be connected through these long strips in the side
that you have to rip off, right?
And we got that back, this epic printout
of all the legal fees.
And we thought, well, what are we gonna do with this?
How are we gonna turn this into a story?
And I don't even know from where,
but I got the idea of just typing it into a spreadsheet.
I think it was probably the first spreadsheet
of my entire life.
And I spent having nothing better to do.
I spent a good chunk of time just hammering all that in
and we added it up.
And at the end, that number got read out on the local news.
The anchor even climbed up a step ladder
and dropped the sort of accordion of paper live on camera,
which was kind of a funny little gag.
And I kind of caught the bug.
You know what I mean?
And within that, I saw that through technology and data,
it was kind of like a way I could help.
It's something I could chip in and do
as a place for me to contribute.
And it also was a gateway to doing more ambitious journalism
than just the average run of the mill story.
We did a story nobody else was doing
that was more ambitious and analytical,
and that was exciting.
And so I kind of just got into it there.
This is now 20 years ago, I guess,
or more than that actually.
And I just followed that and followed that.
And without boring you with my whole life story,
I mean, I kind of ended up on this podcast today.
- Mary Jo, tell us about how you caught the bug.
- Mine is very much a local news-based situation.
I was, I don't know, three or four years into my career
working as a reporter in Oshkosh, Wisconsin,
a very small daily paper.
I was tasked with covering the police and sheriff's department
both on a kind of a policy standpoint,
but also, you know, I went out to the crime scenes
and the fires and whatnot.
But I was covering the city budget
and it looked like the police department
was growing its budget dramatically one year to the next.
And I was sitting there with a calculator
trying to calculate the percent change
between the two years for all of the departments.
And a colleague of mine came over and said,
do you know what Excel is?
And I was like, no, no idea.
He opened it up.
He showed me how to do a simple percent change formula.
My eyes were bugging out.
I was like, wow, this is so cool.
Where did you learn this?
You see, he told me I went to this IRE&NICAR bootcamp
and they teach you all this stuff called,
back then it was called computer-assisted reporting.
And I was immediately hooked
and I decided I had to keep going.
And sometime later that year,
I was able to attend a training that Sarah Cohen did.
She was the IRE trainer at the time.
And I remember sitting in this room.
I don't think it was a hands-on training.
My memory serves.
But I just remember being enthralled
by everything she was saying
and mind being blown by this entirely different way
of reporting that I had not learned in college
that my editors had not taught me in my early years.
And it was a complete turning point for me.
- That's amazing.
Both historical, welcome to the podcast in the first place.
So thank you for being here.
But the stories that you are telling
are similar to some of the stories
that I tell my students that
when you see data journalism or my own field,
data visualization from the outside,
it looks like these very shiny, super advanced,
high technology kind of endeavor.
But when you see how this software is made,
it's actually sometimes pretty pedestrian, right?
It's like you essentially type the data
into an Excel spreadsheet
or you don't use machine learning algorithm.
No, you just use a simple Excel pivot table, right?
So I find all that absolutely fascinating.
I mean, we are going to go back and forth
between your professional careers,
but also other sites of your professional endeavors.
I'm really curious about your educational endeavors
because both of you have been involved
in educational initiatives, right?
Can you talk a little bit about that?
Both of you?
- You mean what training we have taken or the teaching?
- The training that you offer,
because for example, Mary Jo,
you have a data journalism academy, right?
So both of you have been involved
in these types of initiatives.
Not only, I mean, you didn't take advantage
as of things such as like IRE NYCAR,
but you also offered to the community.
- Yes, I am a huge believer in teaching.
I think it has helped me
as much as it helps the other people
because I believe very much in the learn, do, teach approach.
I found all the holes in my knowledge
by having to turn around and teach it to somebody else.
So I've also gotten so much back from other people.
That's how I learned.
So I feel the need to turn around
and teach it to other people.
I have taught for about 10 years as an adjunct
at the University of Minnesota,
a data journalism class that was fully dedicated
just to data journalism.
I'm currently a senior fellow
with the Center for Health Journalism's
Data Journalism Program,
in that we do a week-long training
and then we do six months of mentoring
and additional training throughout that time.
I'm particularly enjoying the mentoring part of that
because it's another level of teaching.
You're helping them get a project off the ground.
You didn't just teach them how to run things in Excel
and then walk away.
You keep it going and help them get a story out the door.
And it's quite fulfilling, actually.
And then I taught at IRE and Nicar a lot
and I built up so many materials
that I've gradually decided I should share those materials.
And at the start of the pandemic
when I had a bunch of free time, I thought,
you know what, it's time to turn some of these materials
into videos.
So I made a new website and posted a lot of stuff there,
mainly Excel and other teaching things.
I am doing a new thing right now
that I'm actually gonna present about this
at the Nicar conference this year.
I've created a little data for editors training module
for the assignment editors in our room.
And so these are the people who work directly
with the reporters, mainly in our local news section.
And I've broken it down.
I'm not teaching them how to use Excel
or how to run data or any of that.
I've broken it down into little sections
of the different points in a data-driven story
that the editor needs to weigh in and look at
and what they should be doing at each point
and what they should be looking for.
So like the key ones are that brainstorming process
with their reporters when they're talking
about what story should I do?
What should I tackle?
Looking, having, I'm giving them some clues
that they should be watching for
that maybe there's a data opportunity here.
What questions they should be asking, things like that.
And then the bulletproofing process.
Okay, the data has come in.
We've got findings.
We're showing you a bunch of charts and tables.
What do you do with it?
Too often the editors just look at it and go,
oh, that's pretty.
Oh, that's kind of interesting.
And I'm trying to teach them like,
how about we take it to another level
and you really help bulletproof it.
And then the third level is the editing the written story.
One of the things I've seen a lot as editors
see a paragraph full of numbers
and they just glaze right over it.
And they don't think about like,
what are we really saying?
What are the key points we're getting across?
So I'm trying to teach them some editing things around,
you know, what's the key finding?
You know, not lumping too many numbers in a paragraph.
All these kinds of things to try to help
make the story more powerful.
And then we're also gonna do a graphic session.
My colleague at the head of our graphics department
is gonna help me with that.
And that'll be more about, okay, when should we use graphics?
What kinds of graphics should we use?
What should you as an editor be doing
when we send you those proofs?
Instead of just saying, oh, that looks beautiful.
What else should you be doing?
And I'm really anxious to see what kind of outcome that gets.
If it leads to more data-driven stories on a beat basis
and more daily basis or a weekly basis,
not just the big enterprise kind of stories.
- What about you, Ben?
Can I talk a little bit about your educational efforts?
- Well, I think Mary Jo said something
very sort of succinct and wise there
with the learn D2, learn, do, teach formulation.
You know what I mean?
It's a great way.
It definitely benefits yourself.
But I also think there's another great thing
about that kind of approach or model
is there's really a very sort of like stimulating
and actually rewarding creative process
of converting something that you've learned how to do
into like a lesson or something
that you can teach someone else.
And it actually is like, it kind of gets the neurons firing
the same way when you're like kind of innovating the code
in the first place for the idea.
And so for me along those lines, you know,
one like sort of approach to teaching that I've enjoyed
or found fruitful is taking emerging new techniques
that we're developing in the newsroom
that I feel like are kind of like a big deal for me
or a big deal for our team,
but that I don't see like being taught
and then trying to convert that
into like a night-card bootcamp or class
to try to spread it to other people.
And so, you know, examples I've done this with not alone.
I always try to seek out other folks
to help me like really strengthen the idea.
But with others, we've created some of the earliest
night-card bootcamps on how to use Jupyter Notebooks,
how to use the static site frameworks
that so many newsrooms use to make standalone visual stories
but like nobody ever talks about, right?
And this year at night-card, we're gonna have,
I think the first kind of three hour bootcamp
on how to automate a scraper
within the GitHub actions framework.
And so to me, like those three things, Jupyter Notebooks,
static site page building, Git scraping
are three really important like technologies
that have taken off in our world
in the last five or 10 years.
And it's just been fun to try to like think about
and pin down, well, how exactly do we use these?
What are the fundamental skills?
How can I pass that on to someone else?
- It's really interesting to me
how you're both so involved in teaching.
And I wonder, does that reflect towards,
I wonder if this is particularly applies to people
working with data on a local level,
is often people are kind of isolated.
Often it's like one or two people on their own,
they've got no support, there's no network.
But the colleagues from other organizations
are kind of struggling in the same way.
So there's a kind of a need there, is that fair?
- I love the psychoanalytical take here.
I mean, I did grow up as a lonely, nerdy kid
on a grand full road side,
who didn't have a lot of friends.
And so maybe this is me still trying to connect,
you know what I mean, and get over.
I was not crazy.
- Well, I think you're right.
There's so many that, you know,
these days they refer to themselves as lonely coders.
The majority of my 20 years in data journalism
was spent in a newsroom where I didn't have support
from anybody else.
And so I sought it out from other people
and learned from other people.
And then, you know, I turned around and taught.
But I think another factor is the Nykar community
has always been a sharing community.
If you even look at how Nykar was formed in the first place,
it was really a group of investigative reporters
who realized they needed to learn how to work with data
and they didn't know.
And a few of them learned somehow, I'm not sure how,
and then they decided to share it with the others
to try to pass it along.
And so it was really, that's how Nykar got started.
And that has been infused throughout all the years.
I remember so many boot camps,
and I think Ben is guilty of this,
of people sitting at the bar at the end of the conference
helping somebody with their data, you know, hovering over
a laptop, helping someone with their data
when they should be, you know, having fun
and enjoying themselves.
But that's how much I think our community likes to share
and teach each other and it just, it's wonderful.
- Yeah, and just to add to that,
I mean, I think if you follow the origins back
like Mary Jo was doing, I mean, data journalism's roots
go a lot further than I think is commonly recognized.
You know what I mean?
It's really a practice that stretches back decades
into the invention of the computer in the '60s and '70s.
And I think is that culture of those early days
is probably in like an anthropological sense,
like indistinguishable from the hacker culture of MIT
that's so celebrated.
You know what I mean?
It really was a very similar people
with very similar sort of ethos of sharing
that is the wellspring for a lot of what we do today.
And I think that, you know, as an inheritor of that,
I'm continuing to be inspired by it
and I feel some obligation to uphold it, you know?
- I think that we all do.
We all have the sort of like feel the need
to contribute back to the community that helped us
at the beginning of our career, right?
I have a question related to what you were both saying
about, you know, growing up as a nerdy kid, right?
I sort of sympathize with that because, I mean,
people don't see where I'm sitting right now,
but I'm sitting in a room with my kid
and then surrounded by comic books, science fiction novels,
you know, books about history and psychology
and then some tabletop games.
So the nerdery comes naturally to me.
So has that improved or has that changed?
It's like, are we still seeing or are you still seeing
as sort of like the nerds in the newsroom
or has that situation changed
and data journalism, data visualization,
computer assistant reporting,
has it has become more widespread and more accepted
or more popular within local newsrooms?
What do you think?
- I think it is more widely accepted
as a tool that every reporter should have in their toolbox.
I like to talk about data analysis
as really another form of interviewing a source.
That's all we're doing really.
And it just requires kind of a little bit
of a foreign language to do it.
I also see a data journalists increasingly
as the innovators in the room.
In all the newsrooms I've been in
for quite a few years now,
the data journalists have been at the forefront
of whatever new digital innovation we're gonna do.
And they're the ones pushing for it and seeking it out.
And in my newsroom right now,
my team is the one often called upon
for like, what do we do next?
Where do we go?
And I think that's wonderful.
And I think that takes us out of the nerdy idea
into kind of more of the leaders.
- Yeah, and you see this in the product realm too,
where a lot of people out of the data journalism world
have become leaders in the next generation
of digital business products
their companies are putting together,
which is a whole other level beyond
just like what's happening in the newsroom.
To be frank with you,
I think in the last two or three years,
we've seen a quantum leap with data journalism in newsrooms.
The takeover has happened.
You see it at the prestige level with those metrics.
You look at the Pulitzer Prizes last year,
five of the Pulitzer Prizes
went to data journalism projects,
including the public service highest award,
which went to the New York Times COVID tracking effort, right?
Which on its own was a gigantic public service
and an incredible feat of like data gathering and analysis.
But it also was the most popular
and I'll say it most lucrative thing
the New York Times has ever published.
And those COVID tracking things
I bet at the Minneapolis paper
was the most popular thing ever published.
I'll just throw that out there.
Mary Jo can correct me.
It's the most popular thing
the Washington Post ever published.
the Los Angeles Times published.
And I don't mean to demean the news by saying that,
but once the product you're creating
is both the high prestige thing
and more importantly, the economic and economic engine.
You know what I mean?
That's growing the digital audience
of which there's a desperate need to grow.
The entire way the organization looks at you changes
just fundamentally.
And that's happening.
- Yes, the tracker we'd put up was,
is hands down the historically most read page
in the history of the Star Tribune.
And the numbers on it are so astronomical
that I don't envision it being that record being broken.
So it would take something pretty massive,
I think to break it.
But the other interesting thing we saw
is that it was also the most popular page
among our digital readers who are not subscribers,
but they come to us pretty regularly
and we would like them to be subscribers.
We call them in tenders.
And it was the most popular page among them.
And now we have conversations going around
what else like that, maybe not data,
but more in the service journalism realm,
but data is one of the things you can do
for service journalism.
What can we do to help get more of those people
to become subscribers?
- Exactly.
This all changed.
And Steve Kornacki was named
one of the sexiest men alive guys.
Come on, we're on top.
Yeah, the dog agrees with that assessment.
So we have talked a lot about COVID on this podcast.
And I wonder what you think the longer term effects
are gonna be for your field
of that very data intensive experience
of working with COVID data in a way that readers
and users actually really responded to.
- I mean, the tracker thing is here to stay.
And I think the creating dashboards for the general public
on major topics they care about is not new.
I mean, it's something that's been around with weather
and sports for a long time.
But I think that it's a type of product
that clearly our audience wants
that is in my opinion, like capital J journalism
in most circumstances, but requires a new assembly line
to be constructed inside the metaphorical factory
of your newsroom to create that.
You know what I mean?
It requires a little bit more
of a product development mindset,
a longer development cycle, a more iterative approach,
you know what I mean?
Than juggling what's on Sunday's front page
and the sort of like day-to-day heartbeat of the newsroom.
And so I think there's a way in which
to produce more of those kinds of widgets,
data journals and teams are gonna have to find a way
to create a kind of app workflow
that's able to support that.
And I think that's becoming more
like a product development team in some ways.
- From a different perspective,
I think it's gonna have a long-term effect in newsrooms
because I think it really woke up a lot of people
to the need and benefits to being able
to analyze your own data
and not rely on a government official
to hand you some numbers on a press release.
Especially in those early days
where we kind of had to pull stuff together ourselves.
But then even more long-term is data literacy,
increasing understanding among reporters and editors
for the need to understand
all the weird little caveats behind data
and the problems we have with denominators and whatnot.
And I think there's gonna be,
I'm expecting to see greater appetite
for data training in my newsroom.
- We talked a lot about how data journalism is affecting
the bottom line for news organizations
and how they're all seeing the value now.
If you're a reader or a user,
you don't necessarily realize
you're looking at data journalism, I guess.
But what difference does it make to them?
Do you think it helps people understand
the local areas better
in ways that we haven't quite kind of grasped
the long-term impact of yet?
- Well, I think the way we present data journalism,
especially in charts and graphs and things like that,
allow people who maybe need a visual aid like that
to see something rather than reading
long sentences of text,
that some readers just do better
with absorbing information that way than others.
And I think also the readers maybe
who aren't naturally inclined to do that
are getting better at it because there is so much of it.
- We all have, oh, sorry, Ben.
Were you going to say something?
We can make a pause.
Let's set this up, okay, perfect.
I was about to say, let's begin there,
we all have projects in our past as professionals
that we are very fond of,
even if they are not perhaps the best projects
that we have ever done,
but there are certain projects that we hold dear, right?
So if you had to choose just one of your local
data journalism projects in the past, right,
what would that be and why?
What was the story about?
What do you do to gather the data or visualize
or display the data, explain the data,
and what type of impact that story had?
- In 2018, we did a series called Denied Justice
that looked at how the criminal justice system
in Minnesota was handling sex assault investigations.
A reporter came to me and said he was hearing
that very few cases that get reported to police
actually result in a conviction, but nobody tracks that.
It's not a number that someone calculates.
So we put in requests for thousands of police
investigative reports and we built our own database,
tracking key bits of information off these cases
and then hunting down, was this referred to the prosecutor?
Were charges filed?
Was somebody convicted?
And a mountain of work in order to get a few numbers.
And what we found is like 8% of reported cases
result in a conviction.
And we ended up doing a series,
it ended up being a nine part series,
which we did not expect,
because it ended up being so powerful.
The response was overwhelming from readers and policymakers.
And we had hundreds of victims come forward
to share their stories because they read our first story
and were like, oh my gosh, I'm not the only one
who had this bad experience with the police department.
I'm not the only one.
This is so cathartic to hear this
and they wanted to share their stories.
And as a result, Minnesota's sexual assault laws
have been overhauled quite substantially.
Several police departments have added additional staff
or like victim advocates embedded into their department,
prosecutors embedded into the department
to help improve the quality of the investigations.
And it was one of the most,
probably hands down the most rewarding
piece of work I've ever done.
At the end of it, we gathered all these victims
at the state Capitol and took a picture
of all of them together.
And these women came out in the bitter cold in Minnesota
in December to do this photo.
And they came up to me and the other reporters
and they were so thankful.
And I've never had that experience before
that the people just thanking us for the work.
And that story is a really big combination
of data being the spine holding up the key findings
and then these powerful emotional stories from victims.
And policy makers told us that the two things combined
were so powerful that they could not ignore it.
- Yeah, when the data comes together
with real life in a way, you know what I mean?
Or when the data leads you to the doorstep
you didn't know you needed to go to, right?
That is just this sort of like unforgettable feeling.
You know what I mean?
It's kind of like one of the deeper work hits.
It's better than any hack, you know what I mean?
And so like for me, like an example of that was
we had a circumstance where there was like
a little political fight in LA government
over the fire department that was really pretty superficial
and was just a couple of people
trying to score political points.
But it raised some questions about the efficacy
of the 911 system in the city of Los Angeles.
And so my colleague and I, Robert Lopez,
decided to get a copy of the entire 911 calls database
and analyze what was happening with the 911 system.
And you know, there's a lot of ins and outs
to how it all worked out.
But the reality was is by doing our own
independent analysis of the data,
we were able to identify several structural flaws
in how the 911 center operates,
how they handle calls near the city border
with neighboring fire departments,
and then go out into the real world tracking real calls,
knock on doors and find out what happened.
And in that we discovered these kind of deeper problems
with the system that nobody was talking about
in city politics.
And we were able to really point to where the system
needed to improve to like make a difference.
And then a change actually did happen, you know.
And to me, that's sort of like that feeling of
where the statistics lead you to the store,
you listen to the numbers,
and then you follow them out into the real world.
And then you connect that with what's really happening there.
And then you bring that back to your audience.
That's better than any chart.
That's better.
You know, I love charts, you know what I mean?
But like, that's better than any little dinky thing.
That's the deeper like thing
that numbers and statistics can lead you to,
which is the sort of hidden truth,
but the deeper story that isn't being told.
And that's the hit, you know,
I'm still looking for it on every story to get back to.
I'm still chasing.
- Those are both examples of stories where a human
is probably not gonna come forward and tell us
that there's a story there.
Maybe they'd have an inkling,
but probably nobody did the data analysis
to know for sure that that's what it is.
And it takes us to do these kinds of lifts
to heavy lifts on data to find those stories.
And, you know, as I said, interview the source
to get at the meat of that story that needs to be told.
- And then sometimes I think this may have happened
in Mary Jo's case too.
Your finding, your synthesis of what's really going on
actually gives a name to and some meaning to something
really negative that happened to somebody.
And then they decide, then your sources
and the people you're writing about
find this deeper reward in the whole thing.
And it's very rare, you know what I mean?
But to me, that's as good as it gets.
- That combination of like traditional reporting
with the data and that sweet spot event have impact as well
is just everything you can ask for, isn't it?
So we are in February, this is our first part of the year.
If you two were to make predictions,
I know everybody does make predictions,
but you two make predictions
about what your big exercise is gonna be this year.
- Let's let Mary Jo off the hook here.
I don't want you to make her pop up too much.
So since I'm working on this new project at Stanford
called Big Local News,
which is really an open source collaborative effort
to try to be a data backbone for all the local newsrooms
who maybe need help or some consulting
or some technology to really pull off big data projects,
we're looking to take it up a notch, Simon.
I mean, I think this year, this team I'm on
with Cheryl and Surdar and everybody up on the farm
in Palo Alto, I'll say it here,
we are going to build the biggest web scrapers
in the history of data journalism.
We're gonna, we have a project called Agenda Watch
where we're gonna scrape hundreds of city council agendas
across the country, put them into one database,
and we're gonna try to do the same thing
with county courthouses.
And you know, those types of projects,
scraping your local county courthouse or city council,
I mean, every local newspaper in America
has wanted to do it.
Some of them have tried to do it.
A very few have succeeded in doing it
for like a short period of time,
but I just don't think that there's been a lasting
and sort of broad solution to that challenge
because it's a lot of work, there's competing priorities,
you know, da, da, da, da, da.
And we're really looking to solve that or try to
by being the sort of database library
that attacks those big things.
And so by December 31st,
we'll be the biggest scraper you've ever seen,
outside of Google, of course.
- I love the Local News Project,
I'm really glad to hear that.
(upbeat music)
Okay, so we are gonna finish off with a new section,
which I'm gonna just call no dumb questions
because these are quite dumb questions.
And they're one word answers,
but I'm gonna go first.
And my one to Mary Jo is,
what book or class had an impact on you
as a professional?
- The Investigative Reporter's Handbook.
- Very good, how about you, Ben?
- Oh, just one?
- Yeah, just one, I'm afraid, sorry.
- Oh, man.
- Be concise, we are all journalists,
we are supposed to be concise.
- Gotta be concise, all right, I'm gonna do it.
I will say the one that had an effect on me,
I will say The Autobiography of Malcolm X
by Alex Haley, guys.
How about that?
It's like a young teenage me,
you know what I mean, moving from the country to Chicago,
getting a broader view of the world.
It was nonfiction journalism
that helped me like see what was up,
you know, and its book is an alternative version
of American history that I hadn't heard before.
It's also a religious conversion story,
not unlike one I've been taught in church,
you know, as a kid who went to Sunday school.
And it shows the power of stories
that go against the grain
that aren't otherwise being told.
And it's a great piece of literature.
So if you haven't read it, you know,
you should check it out.
I think sadly in some ways, you know,
we've regressed since then.
You know, that was a time when Alex Haley
could have the most popular show on television
and write a really provocative book.
And as a reminder of the power,
and I would say virtue of the mainstream media,
when it's properly focused, you know.
- Those were the times.
Okay, next quick question for both of you, actually.
So if you could keep just one of the tools
that you commonly use in your daily job,
what would that tool be?
- R.
- I like that answer.
What about you, Ben?
- Oh, a spreadsheet, guys.
It all begins with a spreadsheet.
You can't play baseball without a bat
and you can't crush data without a spreadsheet.
And--
- Oh, you can, you can, R can do everything.
There's so many things that R can do that Excel can't.
- These R people, they really love R.
Have you guys noticed this?
Like, I think--
- I have actually noticed that.
- Yeah, I think that, you know,
not unlike, that it's like R conversion stories.
It has an evangelical fervor and flavor,
not unlike the Nation of Islam.
- You are only saying that because you're a Python person.
That's the only reason why you're saying that.
I thought you were gonna say Python for sure.
- No, I think it all comes down to the fundamentals.
You know, you can't dribble.
You can't play basketball if you can't dribble.
Can't play baseball without a bat.
I'll give you the religious flavor,
is I'll pick Libre Office's Calc,
the open source free alternative spreadsheet,
which is just as good as the ones from those companies
you maybe have heard of.
- Okay, if you rephrase the question to
what should any journalist have a tool,
I would say Excel.
But what should I, as a professional data journalist,
doing this full-time, crunching numbers like non-stopped,
then it's R.
- All right, okay.
Next one, what is your favorite hack
that you are too embarrassed to admit?
I can tell you my one is,
and I still do this occasionally,
is the way you can use the finder and place
in Microsoft Word as a shortcut to getting stuff done
if you're in a hurry.
I still use it.
I'm slightly embarrassed about it.
So there you go, that's mine.
Ben, do you go first?
- Well, I'm not easily embarrassed,
which maybe is a bug, not a feature in my personality.
But I mean, a hack,
saying no to other people in the newsroom.
You know what I mean?
I think that the data journalists,
especially in smaller newsrooms,
can sometimes get consumed by helping things
just go the way they've always been going
or sort of chipping in around the edges.
And I think that being a helper
and assisting that is noble work and often really valuable.
But I see it pulled back a lot of other data journalists
from really reaching their potential from taking risks
and from doing the more ambitious, powerful work
that our skills are capable of.
So never be afraid to say no
and never be afraid to bet on yourself
and to take a chance.
- I guess I don't know if I'd call this a hack,
but I am probably most embarrassed to admit
that I have data import scripts
that I have not automated, but I probably should.
And I just still keep running them.
It's not exactly by hand, but they're not automated.
I feel like I should be moving into the 21st century,
but, oh well.
- Well, I still run out of patience
whenever I need to style graphs or charts in R
and I export them as PDFs and I style them in Illustrator
just because I find it faster.
So that would be my personal hack.
And I'm not embarrassed at all in admitting it.
So we all have a skeletons in our closet, I guess.
- I had trouble making a graphic in R yesterday
and I was like, ugh, okay, I'm just gonna put it in Excel
and I will make it in Excel.
- I do the same thing with Illustrator.
It's like R is not working, fine.
Let me go to the Illustrator's graphing tool,
which is sort of like the clunkiest graphing tool ever.
So anyway, so let's go to the next one.
What would you have done
if you hadn't gone into journalism?
- Oh, MG, I have no idea.
I've wanted to be a journalist since I was 16, no clue.
- Well, I was not in a very motivated place
before I found journalism as we covered already, Alberto.
But one thing I did like to do at that time in my young life
was read pretentious books and be like a pretentious student.
And so I think at that time, if you had asked me,
I probably would have told you
I would have become a high school English teacher
or something, you know what I mean?
And I don't think that that's a crazy outcome for me.
And maybe I would have been happy doing that.
It's hard to say.
I probably would have stayed in Chicago
and now that I think about it, never met my wife,
which is making me sad to even contemplate.
Like, you know, that's probably it.
- So glad you didn't do that, Ben.
(laughing)
- Oh my God.
My monologue to like high school students
about of mice and men, it would be just terrible.
- I would hope I need to hear that.
Okay, last one, pie charts or tree maps.
And I'm going to go to Mary Jo for this one.
- Tree maps.
- Like anything with visualizations, it depends.
You know what I mean?
Like, so like, I would say like,
well, at first I would say never pie charts
in the circular form.
However, if you have like a single,
like a categorical thing,
I think the like underrated pie chart alternative
is a single stacked bar.
You know what I mean?
Just like one rectangle sliced up.
You can do the nice little labels on the top and bottom.
And I guess it's technically a stacked bar chart,
but it's just a single bar.
It's also a pie chart.
I think those are great.
I think those really work and you can stack them.
It doesn't like Pew do that on their quizzes.
I think that's good.
Cause like, cause maybe that is a tree map.
I don't know.
You guys tell me in some way it is a tree map, I guess,
but like to me the tree map works
when there's a lot of slices,
like there's like 50 slices
and like one or two of them are huge, you know?
And you want to be like, these ones are big
and these ones are small.
But like, if you only have like five things, you know,
you don't need that vertical part of the tree map.
If it's just like a fixed wide height, it works fine.
Sorry, I just did that.
But that's really how I feel about it.
- It's a great, it's a great answer.
I mean, tree maps were created to show a nested hierarchies,
right?
So you have a total
and then you subdivide that total into large divisions,
for example, population of the world.
And then you start dividing them into continents
and each one of the continent pieces
gets further subdivided into the country.
So that's what tree maps are for.
So it's an excellent answer.
I would advocate for the pie chart though.
So just to be the contrarian,
I would vote for pie charts if I could.
Simon, can I do that?
- You don't get advocate for pie charts.
- I did not expect that, Alberto.
- I'm getting old.
Getting older, you know, on a simple pie chart.
I tweeted the other day, if a graphic works, it's good.
And pie charts unfortunately are fortunate, often work.
It's like if there are two, three subdivisions,
four subdivisions perhaps, readers like them,
readers understand them, readers read them,
they bring attention to the data.
So, you know, I'm getting older, more flexible,
more pragmatic in some sense.
So go for the pie chart.
- Even the three-dimensional pie chart?
- No, three-dimensional.
That's going to, maybe when I'm 80.
- That's the limit so far.
- Yeah, that's, no, maybe when I'm about to retire,
maybe I will accept three pie charts.
- Wow, now that Alberto has been switched with somebody else,
I think that's a good point to end.
Ben Welsh, MaryJo Webster, thank you so much.
- Thank you.
- Thank you for having us.
(upbeat music)